RG 021:007, Fairfield Hills Hospital
Connecticut State Library
Fairfield Hills Hospital records
1933-1995
Connecticut State Library
Fairfield Hills Hospital (Newtown, Conn.)
23.5 cubic feet
Fairfield Hills Hospital operated from 1933 to 1995. Includes admission and discharge registers, personnel records, and medical staff records.
RG021_007
Multiple
Historical Note
Fairfield State Hospital in Newtown, Conn. admitted its first patients on June 1, 1933. The hospital was administratively transferred to the new Dept. of Mental Health on Oct. 1, 1953. In 1963 the name was changed to Fairfield Hills Hospital. The hospital closed on December 8, 1995 and patients were transferred to Connecticut Valley Hospital in Middletown.
See also the.
Scope and Content
Series 1. Patients, 1933-1995, includes admission and discharge registers for Fairfield Hills Hospital, as well as for the Berkshire Woods Treatment Center, 1987-1995, which treated substance abuse. The Connecticut State Library does not hold any patient files from Fairfield Hills Hospital. Series 2. Personnel, 1934-1943, contains personnel records of separating employees. Series 3. Medical Staff Records, 1937-1974 includes a record of births, 1951-1975; deportation requests, 1954-1956; autopsies, 1937-1953, and medical examiner cases, 1937-1974.
Arrangement
Arranged into three series: Patients, 1933-1995; Personnel, 1934-1943; and Medical Staff Records, 1937-1974.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Fairfield Hills Hospital (Newtown, Conn.); Fairfield State Hospital (Newtown, Conn.)
Subjects:
Mental health facilities -- Connecticut; Psychiatric hospitals -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Medical records; Personnel records; Photographs
Restrictions on Access
New Exemption: Public Act 11-242, section 37 amends subsection (b) (10) of Conn. Gen. Stat. sec. 1-210 and adds to the exemptions of the Freedom of Information Act any records created as a result of a doctor-patient or a therapist-patient relationship. This closure applies to all records listed below as Restricted.
Patients: Files continue to be made available to patients themselves upon reliable proof of identification which may be a current copy of a Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or current credit card with the patient's name on it.
Families: Section 52-146c of the Connecticut General Statutes allows "next of kin" the right to view records of a deceased patient who was also a relative.
Relatives of deceased patients should contact Assistant State Archivist Allen Ramsey by email at allen.ramsey@ct.gov or send a letter with the following information:
- Full name of the patient.
- Approximate years patient was treated at the hospital.
- Name, e-mail, and telephone of the requestor.
The State Archives will search for the folder and will report the results of the search to the requestor. If a file is found and the requestor wants to view or receive copies of the file, the following information must first be presented to the State Archivist:
- Proof of identity through a copy of a current Connecticut driver's license with a photograph or a copy of a current credit card with the requestor's name on it.
- Proof that the patient is deceased through a copy of a death certificate or obituary.
- Proof that the requestor is a "next of kin" to the deceased patient through a copy of a birth certificate, obituary with the name of the requestor mentioned as a survivor, or a signed and dated notarized statement of relationship to the patient.
Other Parties: According to the new exemption, medical records are closed to other parties.
Record Series Listed Below: Records listed below labeled as non-restricted or unrestricted are open to all researchers who have read the rules of use and signed the registration forms. Since these records are stored off site, they may not be available on the same day.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Patients, 1933-1995
  RESTRICTED
  The Connecticut State Library does not hold any patient files from Fairfield Hills Hospital.
  - Admissions and discharges, 1933-1995; 27 volumes
    - 1996-021, 19 volumes
      - 1933 June-1941 June (Volume Volume 1)
      - 1941 June-1945 October (Volume Volume 2)
      - 1944 November-1947 July (Volume Volume 3)
      - 1947 August-1949 October (Volume Volume 4)
      - 1949 November-1951 August (Volume Volume 5)
      - 1951 September-1953 March (Volume Volume 6)
      - 1953 April-1956 March (Volume Volume 7)
      - 1956 March-1959 May (Volume Volume 8)
      - 1959 June-1961 July (Volume Volume 9)
      - 1961 July-1963 May (Volume Volume 10)
      - 1963 June-1965 January (Volume Volume 11)
      - 1965 January-1966 August (Volume Volume 12)
      - 1966 September-1968 February (Volume Volume 13)
      - 1968 March-1969 August (Volume Volume 14)
      - 1969 September-1970 November (Volume Volume 15)
      - 1970 December-1972 January (Volume Volume 16)
      - 1972 Febuary-1973 April (Volume Volume 17)
      - 1973 May-1974 September (Volume Volume 18)
      - 1974 October-1976 March (Volume Volume 19)
    - 2010-011, 8 volumes
      - Volume 20, 1976 April - 1977 August (Volume Item 1)
      - Volume 21, 1977 September - 1979 February (Volume Item 2)
      - Volume 22, 1979 March - 1980 August (Volume Item 3)
      - Volume 23, 1980 August - 1982 February (Volume Item 4)
      - Volume 24, 1982 March - 1983 December (Volume Item 5)
      - Volume 25, 1983 December - 1986 January (Volume Item 6)
      - Volume 26, 1986 February - 1989 November (Volume Item 7)
      - Volume 27, 1989 December - 1995 October (Volume Item 8)
  - Berkshire Woods Treatment Center admissions and discharges, 1987-1995; 7 volumes; 2010-011
    Volumes covering 1988 July - 1989 June and 1991 July - 1992 June were not transferred to the State Archives.
    - 1987 July - 1988 June, 1 volume (Volume Item 9)
    - 1989 July - 1990 June, 1 volume (Volume Item 10)
    - 1990 July - 1991 June, 1 volume (Volume Item 11)
    - 1992 July - 1993 June, 1 volume (Volume Item 12)
    - 1993 July - 1994 June, 1 volume (Volume Item 13)
    - 1994 July - 1995 June, 1 volume (Volume Item 14)
    - Blank volume (Volume Item 15)
- Series 2. Personnel, 1934-1943
  - Personnel records of separating employees', 1934-1943
    - 1996-021, 9 cubic feet
      - 1934-1939 (Box 1)
      - 1940 (Box 2)
      - 1941 (Box 3-5)
      - 1942 (Box 6-9)
    - 1999-174, 3 cubic feet
      - ABE-HUT (Box 1)
      - HOR-QUI (Box 2)
      - RAN-USH (Box 3)
- Series 3. Medical Staff Records, 1937-1974
  - 1996-021
    - Births and deportation requests, 1951-1975; 1 notebook (Box 10)
      Contents: Births, 1951-1975; Deportation requests, 1954-1956.
    - Autopsies and Medical Examiner cases, 1937-1953; 1 notebook (Box 10)
      Contents: Autopsies, 1937-1953; Medical Examiner cases, 1937 April 23 - 1946 August 31. Lists of names and dates only. There are no details regarding these cases.
    - Medical Examiner cases, 1946 September 1 - 1974 October 28; 1 notebook (Box 10)
      Lists of names and dates only. There are no details regarding these cases.